<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Late letter concerning the sufferings of the Episcopal clergy in Scotland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49682</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13534746</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100042</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240859696</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9151</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13534746</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 461:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Late letter concerning the sufferings of the Episcopal clergy in Scotland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of Scotland.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Persecution --  Scotland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100042:1"/>
            <p>A LATE LETTER Concerning the SUFFERINGS OF THE <hi>Episcopal Clergy</hi> IN SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:100042:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100042:2"/>
            <head>A LATE LETTER Concerning the SUFFERINGS OF THE Episcopal Clergy in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Commands, which declares the Concernment you have for your afflicted Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as in duty I am obliged, so I shall give you as short and true Account as I can of the Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Presbytery of <hi>Stranraver</hi> in the Reinds of <hi>Galloway,</hi> the only Presbytery in the West of <hi>Scotland</hi> which had the Opportunity of giving O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their present Majesties Government, and I shall the more willingly comply with your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100042:3"/> Desire, because the Cases of the afflicted Clergy of <hi>Scotland</hi> touches that but slightly, and promises a fuller Account of that Presbytery. But for a greater Light to what I write to you of that Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, I must intreat your patience, to suffer me to usher it in with a brief Narrative of the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Place in <hi>Anno</hi> 1686. after the time of that Episcopal Parliament, which refused to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>scind the Penal Laws, and so go on until the Ministers there were forced to flee for their Lives, which the Presbyterians are pleased to call Deserting.</p>
            <p>Sir, In that Presbytery there were very few Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters in <hi>Anno</hi> 1686. only the old Lady <hi>Logan</hi> in the Paroch of <hi>Kirkmaden,</hi> and <hi>Margaret Kennedy</hi> Relict of <hi>Thomas Hay</hi> of <hi>Park</hi> in the Paroch of <hi>Stranraver.</hi> There lived at <hi>Stranraver</hi> at that time one Mr. <hi>James Bell,</hi> who in the time of Presbytery had been the reputed Minister of <hi>Kirkcolme,</hi> four Miles from that Town: This Mr. <hi>Bell</hi> was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Presbyterian Preacher which then lived in that Country; who, with his whole Family went to Church, and was one of the Ministers of <hi>Stranra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>'s constant hearers, even after the first Draught of Indulgence came out in <hi>February</hi> 1687. until the two last Lords-days preceding the second Edition: at which time, by the Advice of his Brethren (who posted to each of them their Injunctions) he set up a separate Congregation at his own House; he being at first but only frequented by Women and Children, therefore when any of his Irish Brethren passed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough that Town, either Morning or Evening, he perswaded them to give a Lecture at his House for propagating the good Cause. After their busie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100042:3"/> that way, gaining very few Proselytes, at last there was one <hi>William Torbran,</hi> who, for being concerned in the Rebellion that was on foot in <hi>Anno</hi> 1679. (commonly called the <hi>Bothel-Bridge Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi>) and for murthering a Child of Mr. <hi>Hutcheoson</hi>'s then Minister of <hi>Inch</hi> in <hi>Galloway,</hi> and now one of the Ministers of <hi>Gray-Friers</hi> Church at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> did flee to <hi>Ireland,</hi> but upon the Indulgence return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Stranraver;</hi> this <hi>Torbran</hi> being rich and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, he made a considerable Figure amongst the Inhabitants of that place. He brought off from the Church <hi>John Vans</hi> a present Bailzie or Alderman of <hi>Stranraver,</hi> a Man violent on whatsoever side he be engaged. These two judging Mr. <hi>Bell</hi> unfit to advance the Presbyterian Interest by his preaching, and having assurance that their Indulgence would be continued, they, with the Advice and Concurrence of some Presbyterian Landlords and Ladies, resolved to bring in another Tool fitter for their purpose: And pursuant thereto, after the example of these Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords towards their Farmers, <hi>Vans</hi> and <hi>Torbran</hi> sent for the Inhabitants of that Town one by one, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them to grant the respective Proportions of a stipend they had cast upon them for a Mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the Preacher they designed to call, as those Lairds and Ladies about then had condescended to already; for you must know, the Meeting-house then to be built at <hi>Stranraver,</hi> and the Preacher that was to hold forth in it, was to serve that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Country. As the Farmers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at first refused their Masters, so the People of <hi>Stranraver</hi> at first declined the motion of these two Men; declaring there was no necessity of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100042:4"/> Preacher, whilst they could hear a Protestant Minister in the Church; but what by their Threats and Promises, and fear of loss of Trade, the Lairds and Ladies having prohibited their Tenants from buying any Goods, or employing any Tradesmen but those whose Zeal that way appeared for Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, the greatest part of them were forced at last to submit.</p>
            <p>Sir, as I have told, this was the practise not only of many of the Presbyterian Landlords and Ladies in the Country, but even many of these Gentlemen, who appeared zealous for the Church before they had any prospect of the Indulgences being conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued; but at this time, what by their Wives impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, and the advantage they perceived others got by raising the Proportions their Neighbours cast upon their Tenants or Farmers, to amount to much more than for what they bargained with their Preacher (the Lairds being both the Tax-masters and Collectors) they not only deserted the Church, but become bigot the other way. What the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers gave was no Free-will offering (as the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Preachers gave it out) but meerly forced. There were two Gentlemen in that Country, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en their Common People were appointed by the King's Council to take the Oath of tho Test, these two threatned and beat those Farmers and Tenants, in whom they had any Interest, when they decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they would not take that Oath, and so forced them to do it. And again, when the Indulgence was given them, that they might not be disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Advantage that did accrue to others by their Taxes, they beat the same Tenants from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100042:4"/> Church, and forced them to perjure themselves.</p>
            <p>Sir, You must know the most part of the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords in that Country deal no other ways with their Farmers than as with Slaves, who impose upon them what they please; if the Tenant die rich, the Laird must be Tutor to his Children, or if he die in Arrears to him, then the Laird is Executor, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor, and seizes upon all. So that these Farmers, like the Turks, are not sure if their Children or Relicts shall possess any thing that belongs to them after their Death, for some way or other the Laird Monopolises all</p>
            <p>Such were the Methods of these Oppressors for building their Schismatick Chappels, and to drain the Churches; yea sometimes their Preacher and his Company made their progress through all the Paroches where there were not a Meeting-house, or where there were any Barns nighest the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es there, he preached to affright good People from going to Church, his Company abusing and railing against those that went any way by their Preacher. This was their practice until the landing of King <hi>William,</hi> then their Designs (by the Advice of some wicked Instruments in <hi>England</hi>) being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to raze the Church, and by a Persecution to force the Ministers to flee for their Lives, that the Presbyterians might be armed for that purpose, they forged Sham-plots, which they spread abroad in the West of <hi>Scotland</hi> the Week before <hi>Christmass,</hi> 1688. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> night the 22th of <hi>Decemb.</hi> the People of <hi>Stranraver</hi> had the dismal News of the burning of <hi>Kirkendbright</hi> sent them in a Letter from <hi>John Muire</hi> now Provost of <hi>Air,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100042:5"/> from that Town to the present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whereupon the People of <hi>Stranraver</hi> arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and kept Guard; and that same Night, to strengthen their belief of it, at Twelve of the clock at Night, they had an Alarm that those murthering Papists were entering <hi>Stranraver,</hi> which so terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed those People, that poor Women that had lyen five or six days in Child-bed, in a frosty Night did run out into the Fields only in their Smocks, with their tender Infants in their Arms. Such, by their cruel Shams, was the beginning of their taking up Arms, and the Foundation they laid for a thorough Establishment of their Discipline. Afterwards there was nothing amongst them but Mustering and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercising, that they might be able, as they gave it out, to encounter with the Papists, which in that Kingdom amounts to a very small number; and in the Country of <hi>Galloway</hi> so few (there being none in the Shire, but some in the Stewartry) that one Troop of the Militia carried them all to Joal. But the poor Clergy of <hi>Scotland</hi> have sadly found it, that Bishops and all Episcopal Ministers, and those who frequented the Church, were the Papists (as they are pleased to call all those of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi>) that they made so great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration against; for immediately upon their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up Arms, the Persecution of the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced. Then in Troops they went to Ministers Houses, abused their Persons, spoiled their Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Books, and banished them from their Charges and Livings, and made Havock of all the Clergy in the Western Shires, except that of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway:</hi> for the Gentlemen of that County, not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100042:5"/> fully acquainted with the design of turning out Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, nor what thanks would be afterwards given for doing of it, they sent Messengers to the <hi>Camaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> (the most active People thereabout in that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution) and kept them off the Ministers of the Presbytery of <hi>Stranraver.</hi> None of these Ministers had any visit from them until the Convention of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states adjourned, except one Night, seven of these Reformers went to the Ministers of <hi>Leswalt</hi> and <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme,</hi> and enquiring for Arms, at length discharged them to preach; and about Two of the Clock in the Morning went to the Minister of <hi>Stranraver</hi>'s house, when he was abroad, who broke open his Doors, and with naked Swords and bended Pistols, terrified his Wife and young Children, threatning the greatest Cruelty against them, if that Minister did preach any more in his Church, and if his Wife did not deliver to them what Arms her Husband had, either belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himself or his Brethren, alledging, that because dwelling in a Town, his Brethren for Security would leave what Arms they had with him.</p>
            <p>After this those Ministers continued preaching in their Churches, although they had but very small Congregations; for the news of that cruel Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that Presbytery was to be set up, which the Presbyterians did very industriously spread abroad, did frighten the most part of their People from the Churches into their Meeting-houses. So that they had but Congregations like that of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark, until the Protestants were forced to flee from <hi>Ireland,</hi> then they had numerous Congregations, that place of the Country lying nighest to <hi>Ireland</hi> of any part of the South-west of <hi>Scotland.</hi> After the Proclamation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100042:6"/> came out, appointing all Ministers to pray for their present Majesties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> all the Ministers of that Presbytery (except one who was occasionally absent about his Affairs at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi>) obeyed it, and gave all due Obedience to the present Government in the State: afterwards they continued in the Exercise of their Ministry until <hi>Whitsuntide,</hi> a little before which time the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of that Shire came home from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> fully instructed with all the Fanatick Intrigues. They brought along with them a Commission from the Committee to discharge the present Magistrates of that Town of their Offices, and to cause new ones to be elected in their room. These two Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners called for one <hi>Patrick Paterson,</hi> who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been Mayor or Provost of that Town, who told him they would so far perswade the Inhabitants or over-rule them, as to restore him to his former place, if he would condescend to put the Minister of <hi>Stranraver</hi> out of his Church, and assist them in thrusting out the rest of his Brethren from theirs: which Provost <hi>Paterson</hi> declin'd, declaring he was not so fond of Government, as to accept of it for such Conditions. Whereupon they called upon <hi>William Torbran,</hi> whom I have already mentioned, who but a little time before, was in the Records of that Town bound over to the Peace, for offering to Murther his Son-in-Law, whom he had cheated out of his Patrimony left him by his Father, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring a part of his own to set up for himself, and to live upon. This <hi>Torbran</hi> the two Commissioners judge the fittest Man, and he cheerfully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the Bargain, assuring them they required no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100042:6"/> more of him than what he wished had been done long before; for that Party thought themselves far out, in that their Zeal against the Ministers had not so timously appeared as their provident Brethrens did; yet although they were longer in Executing their Malice upon these Ministers of that Presbytery, then any where else in the West, yet they afterwards sufficiently recommended their Zeal for Presbytery, by the Cruelties and Barbarities in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them.</p>
            <p>These Commissioners, I mentioned, brought with them from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> some Contributions to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed amongst the <hi>Irish</hi> Protestants, who were in great numbers about <hi>Stranraver;</hi> this Money they only give to some of the rudest Fanaticks that came from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that not as Charity either, but as Wages for to abuse the Ministers, and to thrust them from their Churches and Livings; who indeed, although as they pretended to slee from <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reland</hi> for the Protestant Religion, yet did not in the least scruple to persecute Protestant Ministers. There was one <hi>William Ferguson</hi> of <hi>Latterpin</hi> in the Viscount of <hi>Kenmure</hi>'s Regiment, who knew the Country better then any of these <hi>Irish</hi> People, who was sent for to be their Captain; he with his Guards upon <hi>Whitsunday</hi> Eve, went through the most part of the Ministers of that Presbytery, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging them under the pain of Death to preach any more in their Churches; amongst the rest, he went to the Minister of <hi>Stranraver,</hi> after they had bolted the Doors and Windows of his Church, and made him their Prisoner. Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> the Minister inquired by what Order? Whom he answered, That Morning he had come from the Viscount of <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100042:7"/> who, has he had chased away Mr. <hi>Broune</hi> his own Minister, and the rest of his Neighbour Brethren from their Churches, so his Lordship had ordered him to come up, and put the Ministers of that Presbytery from their Churches. Afterwards, calling for the Ministers Gown, and not finding it, he brought him to the Cross, when they came there, <hi>Ferguson</hi> shouted, and cried out, <hi>I discharge you in King</hi> William, <hi>Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>and the Conventions Name, upon the pain of Death, to preach any more in the Church of</hi> Stranraver. To which the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster replied, <hi>If he could have Patent doors he would preach, and would hazard to undergo their Cruelty, rather than desert his Charge, unless he could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him some Warrant from Authority for what he did.</hi> And opening the Proclamation of Estates pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly discharged him to offer any Injury to him, or any of his Brethren conform to that Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he told him was a better Order than <hi>Ferguson</hi>'s invisible one. Upon which Discourse, <hi>Ferguson</hi> offered to tear the Proclamation out of the Ministers hands; upon which he told him, <hi>That he was a proper Servant of theirs, to tear their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Orders, when their private Commands (if there were any such as he alledged) came to be put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, lest they should appear as inconsistent with themselves, as he would make them.</hi> Upon which Discourse an <hi>Irish</hi> Preacher of theirs came up to the Minister, and said to him, <hi>That he and all the rest of</hi> Baal's <hi>Priests</hi> (by that term understanding all Episcopal Ministers) <hi>were too long permitted to live, let be, suffered to preach, and seduce that People any longer.</hi> To which the Minister answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That neither he nor any of his Brethren could
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100042:7"/> be called</hi> Baal<hi>'s Priests; that they had preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Idolatry of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>when they were sinfully silent, out of fear King</hi> James <hi>would have taken away their Indulgence; and while the Church was opposing Popery, they did their best to bring it in: and had the Episcopal Parliaments condescended to Abrogate the Penal Statutes, as the Presbyterians did (notwithstanding they had the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to call them Papists) they would never have got an Indulgence.</hi> Afterwards that Presbyterian Preacher canted anent Calls, and several other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Trash; to all which the Minister answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. These Ruffins not daring, although often times they threatned, at that time to do him harm, because several of his Friends were present, and some good Church People that knew them in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who would have stood up in the Ministers Defence, had they offered any Violence to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: At last, having more Ministers that Night to visit, they were content to dismiss him for that time.</p>
            <p>The next day, not having liberty to preach in his own Church, the Doors and Windows being bolted and guarded, he went to the Minister of <hi>Leswalls,</hi> who being in suspence what to do, his Church Doors were open and without guard, but he was threatned Death if he preached; the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of <hi>Stranraver</hi> undertook to preach for him, which so incensed that Party against him and his poor Family, that a great Party of them came to his House upon <hi>Munday</hi> thereafter, and made search for him and his Gowns, and approaching nigh his Books, which his Wife guarded, lest they should
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100042:8"/> spoil them, they so tossed his Wife, being big with Child, within a Fortnight of her Time, that she fell down in a Swoon amongst their Feet, and they worse then Savages, without regard to her Sex or Condition, most inhumanly stepped over her, without offering to take her up. And they not finding the Minister, and leaving his Wife in so sad a Condition, did drown out his Fire, abused his Houshold Goods and Furniture, throwing out the greatest part of them to the Streets, and by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Proclamation discharged the People of that Town, under the greatest peril, either to lend, sell, or give any thing for the Sustenance of him or his Family. Afterwards, that Afternoon they came se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times in search of Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> and his Gowns; and his Wife recovering, she took the Courage to inquire at them, <hi>What they would do with her Husband and his Gown if they had them?</hi> They answered, <hi>They would pull his Gown over his shoulders, and his Head with it.</hi> And understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they intended to tear his Gown, and to burn it at the Cross of that Town, it being the most publick place in that Country, with the Solemnity of tolling of Bells, and discharging of Muskets: Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi>'s Wife told them, <hi>They needed not be so much offended for want of her Husband's Gown, for rather than they should be disappointed of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity they intended, she would give them one black Gown of her own, which she would more willingly spare than any of her Husbands.</hi> At which, being ashamed, they went away, and troubled her no more at that time. This Troop after this manner wont thorough all these Ministers of the Presbytery of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100042:8"/>
               <hi>Stranraver,</hi> and in what Paroch there were any Presbyterian Preachers, there they thrust the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters not only from their Churches, but also their Houses and Barns, whereof these Preachers imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately took possession. Amongst the rest, they most barbarously abused the Family of Mr. <hi>Nac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smyth,</hi> Minister of <hi>Kirkcolme,</hi> and the Persons of Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> Minister of <hi>Inch,</hi> beating him, and throwing a shower of Stones upon him, when he was going towards his Church; as also Mr. <hi>Young</hi> Minister of <hi>Kirkmaden,</hi> whom they swore by what is sacred, that they would shoot him dead, because he would not deliver them his Gowns, nor would not cut his own Girdle, nor deliver to them the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be burnt, for which Mr. <hi>Young</hi> was set on his Knees to receive the shot from one <hi>Campbell</hi> of <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> who presented, but his Neighbours, with their Muskets turning the Mouth of his aside, when he was a shooting, by God's Providence Mr. <hi>Young</hi> was sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. This Mr. <hi>Young</hi> hath a sickly Woman to his Wife, who hath kept her Bed these Eight years by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, these barbarous Wretches, when they thrust him out of his Manse or Parsonage House, would not allow his Wife the time to put on her Clothes, but threw her almost naked into the Garden; at last, when through the intercession of the Gentlemen of that Paroch, his Wife was permitted to live in the Stable. The Presbyterian Preacher, Mr. <hi>James Wilson,</hi> who took possession of the House, knowing Mrs. <hi>Young</hi>'s Distemper to be a violent Head-ach, that Preacher caused his Servants to go to the Stable door where the sick Gentlewoman lay, who there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100042:9"/> beat upon Platters and other things that could make any Noise to disturb her Head, and increase her Pain, and that not once, but twice or thrice each day whilst she lay in the Stable, near an hour at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very time, tormenting her so that she was sorc'd to hire a House some where else, where she might have the liberty to endure her Affliction peaceably. Which was all the Reparation Mr. <hi>Young</hi> had for building that Stable, and expending thirty pounds sterling in meliorating the Mansion-House.</p>
            <p>Thus after they had thrust all these Ministers from their Churches, and some from their Houses and Barns, their Fury was a little abated until <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> following, when the Commissioners came home, from that Session of Parliament which abolished E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopacy, with new Instructions from the Brethren. One of them told Mr. <hi>William Sommervell</hi> Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who was Minister of <hi>Leswalt,</hi> in which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch that Commissioner lived, that he was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the Road for suffering that Minister to live so long in his Manse (when indeed Mr. <hi>Sommervell,</hi> a good natur'd Gentleman, lived in a Barn at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duff,</hi> a good way from the Manse or Parsonage House, and only his Wife, a neer Cosin to that Commissioner, lived at the Manse, to take care of the Gleab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) and that Commissioner further told that Minister, that they were resolved once to chase all the Ministers out of their proper Paroches, adding, that they might look to themselves, how they came back. And because that Mr. <hi>Sommervell</hi> was so bold as to keep any of his Family about the Manse, that he should cause him meet with a more severe visit e're long: And indeed he was as good
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100042:9"/> as his word (although Sheriff of the Shire, he was obliged to protect those who had given Obedience to the Government) for he hounded out those barbarous Russins upon him, who abused his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Goods, and chased him out of his own Paroch: And when one Mr. <hi>Cleveland</hi> seeing their barbarity, spoke in that Ministers behalf, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided them for their Cruelty, although he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was a rigid Presbyterian, yet they beat him, and wounded him in the Arm, so full were they of Rancour and Cruelty towards the poor Episcopal Clergy, that none dared so much as speak one word in their favours.</p>
            <p>There was a new Fund of Money, fifteen or twenty pounds Sterling sent from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> in <hi>July</hi> with Mr. <hi>Bowis</hi> Minister of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Church, to be delivered to Provost <hi>Torbran,</hi> and his Associates, to be distributed amongst the distressed <hi>Irish</hi> People at <hi>Stranraver.</hi> They conform to their laudable Custom, imploy that Money to bring down some Mountaineers, giving Two shillings a day to each of them to drive every Minister, and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, out of their respective Paroches, that they might not reap their Gleebs, and that their Tythe might come in to their Presbyterian Curates. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Twentieth day of <hi>August</hi> 1689. there went Ten of those barbarous Wretches to Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> Minister of <hi>Inch,</hi> abused his Furniture, and one Mr. <hi>Meikan</hi> so beat his Servant, that he left him almost dead upon the place. Upon the way betwixt <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raver</hi> and the hired Barn where Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> lived, Two of these Wretches did overtake Mr. <hi>Ramsay,</hi> Minister of <hi>Stranraver,</hi> as he was going to visit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100042:10"/> Mr. <hi>Cameron,</hi> and carried him along with them, who came there while they were wounding Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron</hi>'s Servant, and Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> and his Wife, and a tender Infant on her Breasts, in their hands, imploring Mercy from that barbarous Crew for themselves and Servants. When Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> came nigh them they shouted, and with a seeming Joy called to each other, <hi>There is another Dog:</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Meikan,</hi> like a mad man, run towards Mr. <hi>Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say</hi> with his naked Sword, and in a great Fury was drawing a full stroak towards his Head, which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less would have killed him dead, but that by the good Providence of God one of his Fellows, more sober than he, warded off the blow. Afterwards they consulted to shoot these two Ministers, next to tye their hands, and drive them into a Lake nigh that place to drown them, and to rumor it abroad that they did it themselves, and so were guilty of <hi>Felo de se.</hi> At last, by mollifying words, they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded those Savages to forbear their Persons for that time, threatning in the mean time their death if they continued Eight days longer in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, allowing Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> five days longer to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his Furniture out of that Paroch. But a Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger coming from one of the Commissioners, and <hi>Gilbert Moteir</hi> ruling Elder of that Paroch, with Orders not to allow Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> one hour to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his Family; and so they immediately broke part of his Houshold Goods, and cast out his Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture. The reason of that peremptory Message was, because Mr. <hi>Millar,</hi> a Meeting-House Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who preached in two or three Paroches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, was the next day to get a Call to Mr. <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>'s
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100042:10"/> Church, and they must have Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> to desert his Paroch before they could call another. While those Wretches were busied in abusing Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi>'s Goods, Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> got out of the way, and by by-ways got to his own House; for he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard them say that they would lead him in a new Procession. But as for Mr. <hi>Cameron,</hi> they so threatned the People that hired him that Barn (after he had been twice put from his own House, and once out of his own Barn) that those People, or any in his Paroch, when they would very willingly keep and shelter their Minister, yet they dared not lodge Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> and his poor Family one Night longer, that he, his Wife, and tender Infant, were exposed to the rigidity of a cold and stormy Night, having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place to lye in but in the open Air.</p>
            <p>Next day after they had banished Mr. <hi>Cameron</hi> from his Paroch, they went to Mr. <hi>Sommervell,</hi> and treated him as I have already told you, and then to Mr. <hi>Naesmyth,</hi> Minister of <hi>Kirkcolme,</hi> whom after they had put from his Manse, they then put from the Barn he had hired, abusing his Furniture, and would not allow him so much time, as until his Wife should be brought to Bed and recover, who every Minute expected her Paines, and was that Week delivered of a Child. Neither did they spare Mr. <hi>Bowis,</hi> Minister of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Church, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his Endeavours to wheedle himself into their Favours, but as they put him out of his Church, so they dispossessed him of his House, threw out his Goods, and abused his Furniture, the very day before he was going to transport himself and Goods for <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> that he might not have any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100042:11"/> reason to say he went voluntarily away, but as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ministers was forced.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Ramsay,</hi> Minister of <hi>Stranraver,</hi> being informed that Mr. <hi>Millar,</hi> that he might lift his Tythe of the Herrings, and seize upon his Living, intended to hound them out upon him, and to cause them pour the Dregs of their Fury on his Family, while they were making their progress in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, chasing the Shepherds from their Flocks, that the Wolves might more easily devour them, reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him to the last Scene, because in a publick place; he was forced to flee to <hi>Ireland:</hi> But what through their outragious Carriage, and affliction his Wife was in for fear of his life, she contracted a Fever, which went thorough his whole Family; and yet when absent, and his poor Wife and three young Children were lying at the point of Death, Mr. <hi>Millar</hi> seized upon his Tythe of the Herrings; and in that deplorable Condition his poor Family was in, <hi>Millar</hi> would not allow them the value of one of Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi>'s Herrings to succour their lives. Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> continued two Months and a half in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and served the Cure of <hi>Donoghadee</hi> for Mr. <hi>Maxwell,</hi> who was then Chaplain to Colonel <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Regiment; and when the Camp at <hi>Duno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk</hi> broke up, and Mr. <hi>Maxwell</hi> returned home, hearing that something of the Presbyterian Fury was abated, he went home to his distressed Family. But he, and those Ministers who lived at <hi>Stranraver,</hi> were in such a Condition that they could scarcely live, for they would give them nothing of their by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone Stipends for a present Subsistence, they would not give so much to Mr. <hi>Ramsay</hi> as to pay the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100042:11"/> of one of his Children, when he died. Yea, so cruel and unjust were they to the Ministers in that Country, that the Sheriff encouraged all those to whom they were owing any thing, to sue them before him and his Deputy, and sentenced them to make payment; while on the other hand he refused to hear them as to their pursuit of bygone Stipends, that they might have wherewith to pay their just Debts, and nourish the Lives of their Families, which reduced them to the most pinching Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, so that they were forced to sell the Furniture of their Houses at low Rates to pay their Debts, and supply the Necessities of their Families. Sir, when they were wearied with mobbing the Ministers, and their Fund of money failed to pay their Souldiers, when the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> went home; at last, ashamed any further to abuse the Persons of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, and to banish them out of the Shire, as well as Paroches, they at last took that method to starve them out of that Country; a Cruelty intollerable, and of which the very <hi>Turks</hi> would have been asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be guilty.</p>
            <p>Sir, This is a true Account of the Persecution of the Presbytery of <hi>Stranraver;</hi> and had it not been for imposing upon your Patience, by a longer Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, I could have added many more considerable things in that Persecution, which would almost sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass the belief of sober Christians, that those who make such glorious pretences, as to be the only People of God, should be so unlike God, and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of such monstrous Barbarities, as they can scarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge the most Savage Infidels with the like: But what I have wrote, I am able to prove, when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100042:12"/> called, by many unacceptionable Witnesses, and maugre their Malice and common Impudence to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Truth of what makes against them; when questioned, I shall make this, and much more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as also, the Persons and Names of those, who were either the Projectors, Abettors, or Instruments of this Persecution to their Infamy and Disgrace.</p>
            <p>Sir, I thought to have given you a short Account of the general Persecution of the whole Clergy, which might be reduced into four Classes. 1. Those persecuted by the Mobile before the 13th day of <hi>April,</hi> 1689. and not noticed by the Estates, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally neglected, as Deserts, and left without the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Government, as the Conventions Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, dated the said day, does sufficiently insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate. 2. Those who complied, and were persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Rabble, as the Presbytery of <hi>Stranraver,</hi> and many Ministers in the East and South of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> or those, who after they complied, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived by the Councel, because they did it not on the individual day appointed, when the Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came not to their hands against the time requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor could they have the opportunity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it sooner, then when they obeyed it; as Mr. <hi>David Young</hi> a Minister in <hi>Pearthshire,</hi> the Minister of <hi>Torryburne,</hi> the Minister of <hi>North-Berwick,</hi> and several others. 3. Those who were deprived by the Councel for not compliance, there being not so much as 24 hours given some of them to advise on so weighty an Affair. 4. Those who are now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the holy Inquisition of the Presbyterian Preachers; of each of which I could give you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sad Instances, and with what hard measure they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100042:12"/> have been treated: But because the Instances of the first three Classis, are already in print, and those of the last Classis shortly coming out. I shall only trouble you with a short Account of Mr. <hi>Douglas,</hi> who you know is now in <hi>England,</hi> who was mobbed before the 13th of <hi>April,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>Sir, In the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> 1688/9. upon a <hi>Munday</hi> there came to <hi>Skirling</hi> Seventy <hi>Camaronians</hi> and surrounded Mr. <hi>Douglas</hi> his House, and forced open his Doors, and after many approbrious Speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es belched out against him, and all the Episcopal Clergy, they discharged him to preach any more under the hazard of his life; yet afterwards Mr. <hi>Douglas</hi> continued preaching for several Lord's days, but under such Apprehensions of their Fury, that he was forced to retire all the Week from his own House, and abscond; but they receiving Information that he preached after they discharged him, in the beginning of <hi>March</hi> thereafter, on a Lord's day after he had done with Sermon, they came again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Skirling,</hi> thinking to find Mr. <hi>Douglas</hi> at the Church, but having timous Advertisement, and a Horse ready at the Church Style to leap on, before they came to that Town, he escaped to <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> wherefore being disappointed, they set Watches for him in every Corner to murther him, if he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to return to his Church and House, so that he was forced to stay at <hi>Edenburgh.</hi> But it was not enough that they had affrighted him from home, but next they came upon his Wife, threatning her with the greatest of Severities if she did not depart out of that House and Paroch; but at last, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a little time for transporting her Family and Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100042:13"/> she wrote to her Husband for his Advice; who knowing the Severities his Neighbours met with, and what murthers and slaughters had been committed by that hellish Crew, and following the advice of our Saviour, when we are persecuted in one City to flie to another, he wrote to his Wife to transport her self and Family as soon as possible to <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> where yet she continues, since he came to <hi>England;</hi> and notwithstanding of this Severity done him and his Family, he is neglected by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, left without the protection of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by this current Parliament, in its last Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, called a Deserter.</p>
            <p>Sir, Notwithstanding of this cruel and barbarous Persecution, of which I have but given you a very small and imperfect Account, it being much sadder and more afflictive then I am able to express; yet after repeated Complaints thereof to some of those intrusted for present with the Government in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> no Redress could be had, nor Consideration taken thereof, but to the prejudice of those Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters who were not then involved in so sad Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances; for a new Petition occasioned a new Snare for intrapping those, who had not been as yet catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Nets, and no relief afforded those under the lash; but their business waved, or if some sham Redress was proposed then under hand, some dealt with those Parochiners, whom it concerned, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the same ineffectual: As in the Case of the Minister of <hi>Bogie,</hi> when the Heritors of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch protected him against the Mobile, a great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son wrote them a Letter, forbidding them to assist their Minister, but to suffer the Rabble to take their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100042:13"/> Course; which Letter his Grace, my Lord Duke of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> produced at the Councel Table to the consternation of the Person who wrote it. And when Complaints were given in, that Person who wrote the said Letter, would not suffer them to be heard, but would tell the Complainers, That the Common People were inraged, and now when they had the opportunity, they would revenge themselves, and it were not fit at this time to contradict them.</p>
            <p>What Reasons were given them by our Clergy, the two last Reigns to provoke them to lay aside all Humanity, and against the common Rules of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, let be Christianity to become so cruel and barbarous, I am altogether ignorant; and I am sure our Clergy are able to defie them to give one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, where any Dissenter suffered Death, or were any ways injured by the Information or Instigation of any Minister of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or that any Dissenter did suffer purely for dissenting, but only in the Case of open Rebellion, which being destructive of Civil Government, no Civil Magistrate can tolerate; or in the Case of the murder of Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi> Archbishop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> or the wounding Dr. <hi>Honnyman</hi> Bishop of <hi>Orkney,</hi> with a poysoned Bullet, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned his Death; or the murther of Mr. <hi>Peter Peirson</hi> Minister of <hi>Carspherne</hi> in <hi>Galloway;</hi> or the murther of Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kenneway,</hi> two Gentlemen of the King's Life Guard at <hi>Swine-Abby;</hi> or the horrid butcheries and murther committed on the Person of Mr. <hi>Blair,</hi> one of the Duke of <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Chamberlains, they ripping up his Body alive, and taking out his Bowels, at his own House; or the barbarous Cruelties committed upon the Persons of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100042:14"/> Mr. <hi>Lawson</hi> Minister of <hi>Irongray,</hi> whom, after he had plentifully entertained them at his House, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lame man, they brought out and wounded him in nineteen several places of his Body, whereof thirteen were in his Head, leaving him in their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension dead, although afterwards by God's good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to the admiration of all men, he recovered; as also for their barbarous Cruelties committed upon Mr. <hi>Ramsay,</hi> then Minister of <hi>Auchinleck,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shaw</hi> of <hi>Ainworth,</hi> and several others; and yet when any of them were punished for these notorious Crimes, as the Authors, Abettors, or Actors, the Clergy never appeared against them, either as Judges, Accusers, Party, or Witnesses. Yea when the Government com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Clergy to inform against those People, they generally declined it, until at last, when the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice Courts went thorough the Country, they sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned the Clergy to give in Catalogues of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiners and Dissenters upon Oath, or otherwise to be committed to Goal, to abide Trial for disobeying Authority; so that being upon Oath forced to give in the Names of Dissenters, yet they did it with such excuses and mitigations, that very few ever suffered, either in their Persons or Estates, upon their Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which sufficiently testified the Ministers aversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any thing that in the least might give them reason to suspect them in having any dealing in what was inflicted on them by the Government. Even oftentimes the Ministers imployed their power and moyen to save them when accused; and now those who by their intercession escaped, will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge those Ministers as active Instruments, but tell them it was against their Inclinations to save
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100042:14"/> them, and that God forced them to do what they did, as <hi>Andrew Ross,</hi> Son to <hi>John Ross</hi> of <hi>Carnebrock,</hi> told Mr. <hi>Naesmyth,</hi> who saved his Father, and pleaded of a Fine that was to be imposed upon him; and as several others speak to their Benefactors; all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that Mr. <hi>Naesmyth</hi> got for his kindness, was, that the same <hi>Andrew Ross</hi> told Mr. <hi>Naesmyth,</hi> that it was not fit that either he, or any other Minister, should be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to live in that Country, least they might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards do them harm, and give information of their designs. And indeed, Sir, those who escaped by the intercession of any Minister, are now become the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Enemy and Persecutor that such a Minister hath, as that <hi>Andrew Ross</hi> caused to draw up a Summons to that Minister to depart from his Church and Manse, and was the great cause of all those Troubles that Mr. <hi>Naesmyth</hi> met with since. Sir, for all the loud clamors of a Persecution against the Presbyterians in the two last Reigns, I can confidently affirm, and am able to prove, the Episcopal Clergy were the only Persons persecuted all the time, either in their Names, Goods, or Persons, several of them murthered, some wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and others affrighted from their Houses, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in frost and stormy Nights to wander about for fear of their lives. And indeed, because the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians were not suffered, without punishment, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant Government, murther, plunder, and defame, then they rung it abroad that they were persecuted; and because the Episcopal Clergy was established by Law, and countenanced by the Government, as more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant to Monarchy, and of more Apostolical, quiet, and better Principles than the others; when only the Civil Powers took cognizance of the Fanatick crimes, therefore they gave it out, that by Prelacy they were persecuted.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100042:15"/>
            <p>Now they change their Note, and sound it abroad that Episcopacy was an intollerale Grievance to that Nation, and they had reason so barbarously to abuse the Clergy of <hi>Scotland,</hi> because intruders, Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being the ancient Church Government of that Kingdom, and by which it was reformed.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if their Argument were as true, as they have the affrontary to affirm it, yet when we consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Scotland</hi> was reformed in a tumultuary way, and against the will of the Supream Magistrate, because they pretended only to be Presbyters who had the chief hand in the Reformation, if it follow that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Presbytery ought to be the Church Government, the Argument will as well hold that the Government should be Anarchy and Confusion in the State, and the Civil Government should be as confused and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuary, as Presbytery in the Church, is sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to be; and we may fairly guess whether these men tend at last, who make the pretence of a Presbyterian Reformation, for setting up Presbytery in <hi>Scotland;</hi> that if King <hi>William,</hi> or any other Prince, offer to curb them when insolent (which is a common vertue amongst them) if it be in their power, they will not stand to set up as fair a Plea for Democracy in the State, which they may as rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally urge upon the same principle that they plead for Presbytery in the Kirk. And indeed King <hi>James</hi> the Sixth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and First of <hi>England,</hi> who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood them very well, and did see thorough their Designs, and was partly disciplin'd by them, in his <hi>Basilicon Doron,</hi> can tell us, that they are the Pests of the Commonwealth, as well as Church. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Favours have been hitherto conferred on them, will never be able to secure them; if they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100042:15"/> in the least Extravagancy for the future. King <hi>James</hi> and his Son King <hi>Charles</hi> may be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Lessons to their Royal Successors King <hi>James</hi> from his own Experience in his <hi>Basilicon Doron,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, That no Deserts will oblige them, nor Oaths nor Obligations bind them; and then in that <hi>Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of his to the Prince, protests before the great God, that the wild Highlanders and Border-thieves, were not so unthankful, nor guilty of more vile lies and perjuries, then these Fanatick Spirits. And alas! we found it too sad a truth; that in so far as that glorious Martyr King <hi>Charles</hi> the First receaded from the Golden Rules which his Royal Father wrote in that Book for the Government of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that blessed Prince advanced so many steps towards his Martyrdom. Nor is it to be imagined, that the Presbyterians now in <hi>Scotland</hi> are more moderate than their Predecessors (which all good Christians would have wished) but their Cruelty towards the poor Clergy there, their engaging Parents at the Baptism of their Children to bring them up conform to their Covenants, and with Rules, and others Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to purge <hi>England</hi> of Prelacy and Superstition, as well as <hi>Scotland,</hi> are clear indicium's of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that they are of the holy and covenanted Seed, and degenerate nothing, but exactly trace the glorious footsteps of their Forefathers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to their pretence, That <hi>Scotland</hi> was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Presbyters. I would inquire, who Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained these Presbyters? Whether Bishops, or not? If they were not ordained by Bishops, what Miracles did they work to prove their extraordinary Mission, that I may believe them to be Presbyters, as they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100042:16"/> give it out? If they were ordained by Bishops, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called a pure Presbyterian Reformation, for I suppose, which none can deny, they were obliged to preach the Gospel, as the Bishop who conferred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon them, bound them thereunto. And that the Gospel was preached at the Reformation first by Presbyters, from thence to infer their Exemption from Episcopal Jurisdiction for the future, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to abolish that Sacred Order, is such an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference as might have justified the <hi>Samaritans</hi> and <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> if they had set up only the Government of Deacons in their Churches, and had rejected the Authority of the Apostles, because they were at first converted by <hi>Philip</hi> a Deacon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That these Premisses are as false as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion is which they draw from them, will appear, in that <hi>Scotland</hi> had several Bishops who reformed, <hi>viz.</hi> amongst the rest Dr. <hi>Gordon</hi> Bishop of <hi>Galloway,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> Bishop of <hi>Orkney;</hi> that the latter reformed, we have an undeniable instance in that of the Consistories offering to Excommunicate him for marrying Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Bothwell;</hi> and it were a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to Excommunicate one who was not of the Protestant Communion. Further, in those places where Popish Bishops were possessed of the Revenues at the beginning of the Reformation, there were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Bishops appointed in their places under the Name of Superintendants, who had the power of Ordination and Jurisdiction lodged in them (although I must confess they were not consecrated by other Bishops) yet none could ordain or exercise Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction without them, which sufficiently testified the humour and opinion of these times against a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100042:16"/> Parity; for these Superintendants went up and down their particular Jurisdictions holding Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and exercising Discipline, and had a larger Maintenance allowed them than other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, upon the account of their Dignity and Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in travelling to their Visitations. The other B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of that Kingdom sate in Parliament, and there represented the Clergy, the first Estate thereof. There was scarce any mention of the <hi>Geneva</hi> Discipline, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til in the Year of our Lord 1575. Mr. <hi>Andrew Melvill</hi> brought the same to <hi>Scotland,</hi> whom <hi>John Durie</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betted at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> no doubt, being a popular man, because he missed a Superintendency. So that as for the Antiquity of that Pageant Government of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Reformation was not only begun, but also fully settled for many years under the Government of Bishops and Superintendants, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1592. was forced to set Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery up, by the importunity of a factious Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who were still abusing him, each different Party taking possession of his Royal Person, until they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to grant their Demands. But then that wise Prince recovered his Liberty, and more command of his own Person and Judgment, he set himself in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest about the Restauration of that truly Ancient and Apostolical Government of the Church by Bishops, which out of all our impartial Historians, will suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appear to any unprejudged Readers.</p>
            <p>Sir, The sad Account which I have given you of the Prsecution of the Scotch Clergy, although it be not fully, but imperfectly represented by me, yet methinks it is so great, as to move compassion in any Christian heart towards them; but more especially, if we consider
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100042:17"/> that not only they are forced from their Livings, and their Persons abused, but also by those <hi>Machiavelians</hi> murthered in their Names and Reputation; an Injury more grievous than Death it self; it being the design of those vile Lyars and Slanderers, not only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatter a whole Church, (the greatest impudence i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable) but also so to blacken them, as that they may be esteemed the greatest Criminals in the world, that their Cruelties might be excused, and those Ministers deprived of that Pity and Compassion that their Calamity would move from the most Savage Breasts but that of the Presbyterians, which is the severest of all Persecutions. God be thanked, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Reproaches of their implacable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, I am able to affirm, that they suffer not as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doers, neither for the manifest Breach of Divine or Humane Laws, but only for that Venerable and Sacred Order of Eiscopacy, and their Zeal for the Church against the Fanaticks of the Kirk, which I hope you, and all true Sons of the Church will so consider, as to afford them your Prayers and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for their Restoration and present Relief.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>